Guide to the Woodbine Home Demonstration Club records, 1961-2008
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
Woodbine Home Demonstration Club records
1961-2008
C0303
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center.
3.0 linear feet (6 boxes)
Minutes, photographs, scrapbooks, and realia from the Woodbine Home Demonstration Club, a homemakers' organization.
Woodbine Home Demonstration Club.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by the Prince William County Library in November 2016.
Historical Information
The Woodbine Home Demonstration Club of Prince William County, VA was born of a wider movement across the United States - Elizabeth Griffin Hill notes that "Home Demonstration Clubs were an integral part of the U.S. Department of Agriculture Cooperative Extension Service, which was established during the early 20th century as an experiment in adult education, providing agricultural demonstration work for men and home demonstration work for women" ('Home Demonstration Clubs'). According to a history by Louise Benton (a long-time officer and member) included in Box 3, Folder 6 of the collection, the Woodbine Club formed from the merger of two different home demonstration clubs in 1941. The organization was also known as the Woodbine Extension Homemakers Club and later as the Woodbine Family, Community, and Education (FCE) Club. Over the years, the women of the group gathered regularly, held meetings and events, and raised money for numerous charities. As of 2017, the Woodbine FCE club has disbanded.
Scope and Content
The collection is largely made up of scrapbooks, meeting minutes, photographs, and realia kept by the Woodbine Home Demonstration Club of Prince William County, VA between 1961 and 2008. The social and charitable activities of the club from the 1960s to the early 2000s are well documented in the records. Of particular interest in one of the scrapbooks from 1978-1979 is a letter from the White House congratulating club officer Louise Benton on her designation as Homemaker of the Year. VHS tapes and a DVD on charitable programs and the dedication of Louise Benton Middle School are also included.
Bibliography
Arrangement
The collection is largely arranged by format.
Related Material
The Special Collections Research Center holds other collections donated by RELIC at the Prince William County Library, including the, the, the, and the Prince William Historic Newspapers collection.
Index Terms
Geographical Names:
Prince William County (Va.)
Subjects:
Domestic life.; Home economics extension work.; Home economics.; Women--Societies and clubs.
Document Types:
Color photographs; Scrapbooks.
Contents List
- Minutes recorded by secretaries, November 1965-October 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Minutes, meeting information (1 of 2), January 1970-November 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  some pages may be out of chronological order due to sleeved pages falling out of the folder
- Minutes, meeting information (2 of 2), January 1970-November 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Woodbine Extension Homemakers Club minutes, 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Histories, minutes, members, correspondence, etc. (1 of 2), 1996-2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Histories, minutes, members, correspondence, etc. (2 of 2), 1996-2006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Family and Community Education Achievement Day programs, various other brochures, funeral bulletin, 1992-2008 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Family and Community Education newsletters, meeting minutes, photos, etc., 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Items pertaining to naming of Louise Benton Middle School, 1979-2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Yearbooks/handbooks, Family and Community Education Achievement Day program, 2 photos (1 of 2), 1979-2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Yearbooks/handbooks, Family and Community Education Achievement Day program, 2 photos (2 of 2), 1979-2002 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Club scrapbook (1 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Club scrapbook (2 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Club scrapbook (1 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Club scrapbook (2 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Duties of club officers (2001), newsclippings, scrapbook, etc. (1 of 2), 1961-2002 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Duties of club officers (2001), newsclippings, scrapbook, etc. (2 of 2), 1961-2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Photos, postcards/brochures/programs, activities, circa 1970s-2003 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Historical items on Woodbine FCE Club, 1999-2003 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- 3 VHS tapes, 1 DVD on various charitable organizations/naming of Louise Benton Middle School, circa early 2000s (Box 4)
- Gavel, two key chains, Benton Cougars cup, school kit instructions, circa 1970s-2001 (Box 4)
- Scrapbook and Scrapbook pages, 1999-2003 (Box 5)
- Two signs, circa late 1990s-early 2000s (Box 5)
- Scrapbook, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
- Scrapbook, 1978-1979 (Box 5)
- Smile doll and description, circa 2003 (Box 5)
- Scrapbook, 1964 (Box 6)
- Scrapbook, 1997-2002 (Box 6)
- Scrapbook, 2004-2008 (Box 6)
- Virginia and United States flags, undated (Box 6)